the most interesting intellectual
endeavors you could embark on at our
current time it is right at the
intersection of AI and a natural
language processing or machine learning
and so when we think about you know what
are sort of the most interesting
manifestations of our human intelligence
I think language comes up at the top for
most in most answers it is very
inextricably linked to thought and also
information and you know we're an
Information Age so natural language
processing is an immensely useful piece
of technology at the same time deep
learning is similar in the sense that it
is very broadly applicable you can do
speech recognition with deep learning
you can do image pacification and you
can do a lot of different tasks inside
natural language processing so deep
learning is also a very very interesting
tool for you to have going forward in
your lives and so basically we're
combining these two so it will both be
interesting from an academic and
intellectual perspective as well as for
industry there are a lot of companies
out there right now who are trying very
hard to hire people with deep learning
skills so I think hopefully this will
help you both if you decide to work in
an academic setting or an industry
setting so basically by the end of the
lecture you will be able to build an
algorithm that can kind of do what you
can see here which is it can interpret
the sentence like the first 50 minutes
were dry but by the end I really enjoyed
the lecture and so the algorithm here
learned what the grammatical structure
of that sentence should be and it
assigned a label which in this case
happens to be a sentiment label - every
phrase of that sentence and will
basically give you an introduction of
why the tree looks the way it does and
why it assigns these positive and
negative labels so what's kind of
amazing here is we did not have to
eventually say that you have here a so
called contrastive conjunction name but
but really we just had to give it a lot
of examples and I was able to learn that
really you can say the first part is
negative and you know the first 15
minutes
that is a neutral phrase and then once
you say they were dry it becomes
negative and then you have a contrastive
conjunction which usually which usually
means that what comes afterwards matters
more in the overall interpretation of
the sentence none of that we have to
explicitly tell the algorithm but it
will be able to pick it up and you will
train algorithms that will be able to do
that and just as the sentence says we'll
start with a couple of boring logistics
but you know they're important for you
to understand what's going on moving
forward and then we'll actually
introduce in an almost ridiculously
short amount of time natural language
processing deep learning and the
intersection of the two
so let's dive
right in
my name is Richard so sure I actually
got a PhD from Stanford last year and
happen to work on deep learning for
natural language processing and a little
bit of computer vision I'm now the
founder and CTO of meta mind which is a
startup that also happens to do deep
learning for those two application
fields we have three awesome TAS maybe
they can wave their hands we get Ian
back there and within the camera from
SWA and poong right there so we'll have
four office hours at least
if the enrollment stays as high as it is
maybe we'll get a fourth one because
it'll be a lot of grading otherwise for
you three I'm sorry we had to change the
time in place we originally had a room
from the 60 people and now we have
hundred 60 people students enrolled so
we had to move to this I hope it's not
too bad we'll try our best to actually
record all the all the lectures on video
and put those up we still need to figure
out if we can just put them on YouTube
well soon find out hopefully this week
we will have a lot of problem sets so
basically three problem sets that will
make you basically program these kinds
of algorithms and there will be a
midterm and a final project and in fact
the final project is something that you
might want to start thinking about
starting today this is going to be an
important part and hopefully as we go
over a bunch of applications you'll see
you know you have some ideas on what you
want to do you can find our office hours
and soon also office hour
locations on the website I'm sorry that
will probably not be any course notes
but we will put up the slides and the
videos shortly after and if I'm on top
of my things maybe even before the
lecture
----- 3 ------
so the grades for those of you
who take not a pass/fail we basically
have the three problem sets that count
for roughly 1/2 and the midterm is 15%
the midterm we want to make sure you
actually understand some of the very
basics of the math behind behind what
you're programming in the problem sets
the final project will be 40% we have a
milestone and usually when you start out
your project definition you say oh I'm
gonna solve NLP it's gonna be so great
and epic and then we have the milestones
and what we often then get I was a TA
for 229 in machine learning classes
we're struggling collecting the data and
that is actually it's a very common
problem a lot of these algorithms need a
lot of data and just dealing storing a
lot of data might not fit on your laptop
you might need some other machines so
we're going to give you two bonus points
or percent of the entire class if you
have your data ready and run a single
experiment could be just a simple
baseline if you actually have yeah some
experiments done at the time of the
milestone and then the final write-up
project and presentation will have a
poster presentation instead of the final
will be 35 percent are there any
questions so far
all right so yeah bonus points also for
exceptional poster presentations delayed
policy we're trying to not have to hear
about your grandmother so we'll give you
seven free late days you can use them as
you please
except that you can only use three for
one problem set at a time so after three
days we want to basically talk about the
solutions during the office hours and
want to move the class along because the
next problem said will be do you know
two weeks after and oftentimes they
built on top of each other so you want
to be able to share the solution so you
can turn your problem sets in at most
three three days late after you either
exceed those or you hand it in
no so once you hand it in late it's gone
instead if you exceed your seven late
days you will lose 25% per late day
after that and it unfortunately cannot
apply to the final course project
because we have to put in the grades
into the system so collaboration policy
Stanford recently got into the news not
so pleasantly so please do read your
codebook and the honor code obviously
you can you know talk about things
during a lecture and your understanding
but you have to write down the own
solution and most importantly have to
program your own solution and not try to
find some code somewhere on the internet
or something like that
on the final project you can actually
work in teams of two people and maybe if
you have a really ambitious project and
you have a very clear setting of what's
going on we can make an exception and
have three but ideally you'll just be
two because otherwise it's hard to
attribute who did what all right any
questions about all the grading
--- 5 ---
great alright so prerequisites on a very
high-level note I will rather air and
decide of boring some people in the
beginning and you know make sure
everybody gets the very basics of the
math and the programming so if you have
taken all the prerequisites and you've
got a pluses in all of them and you know
that was all pretty boring because you
already kind of knew it I unfortunately
you will be a little bored in the first
like handful of lectures maybe to what I
found
seeing is it's better to err on that
side and then we can you know ramp up
the speed as we go to more complex
models really once you know some of the
basic building blocks off deep learning
you can very quickly put them together
in interesting new ways they're kind of
LEGO pieces you just need to understand
how they're put together and then build
amazing stuff so that being said you
will have an easier time if you're
proficient in Python all the class
assignments will be in Python will use
numpy but obviously not packages likes I
could learn because that's the kind of
stuff we want to learn how to do
ourselves so we will you know provide a
tutorial here actually from a previous
class to 31 and and so let me ask in the
room show of hands who would want to
have a Python refresher to make sure
their can hit the ground running raise
your hand okay who does not need a
Python refreshment
all right well it does seem like there
are very few people who really need it
so maybe those people in the interest of
our th time I can just talk to some of
the TAS they're only like a handful of
hands raised
hmm and yeah during office hours of
course yeah all right college-level
calculus and linear algebra will be
great
so who here no singular value
decomposition all right all right I'm
that's this is awesome all right you'll
have you'll have a great time on
Wednesday because well we'll kind of
assume that that you know SVD and we can
then move to to neural networks more
quickly so basic probability and
statistics is also good you don't need
to know crazy lebesgue measures or
anything for deep learning but you know
knowing what the you know log likelihood
is and things like that will make your
life a lot easier and really if you've
have fully understood CS 229 in all its
gory details you'll have a lot easier
time in general conceptually moving
through this class we'll have a lot of
cost functions and basically once we
write down our cost function everything
else will be kind of straightforward you
take derivatives sort of a bunch of
matrix multiplications and then you run
some optimization algorithm like
gradient descent any questions on the
prerequisites
-- 10 --
all right so that was the boring part
and I'm very hopeful from the hands
being raised so far that we can move
somewhat quickly through through the
early parts of the class material so
what is natural language processing
again these are very very short
descriptions and in some ways it's still
a reasonably young field so the the
definition is is a little bit subjective
but most people I think would agree with
the minimum subset here that that I
describe which is that natural language
processing is a field at the
intersection of computer science
artificial intelligence and linguistics
you will often find researchers working
in NLP to be associated with these kinds
of departments and you know in some
cases some universities have an AI or
machine learning Department and most
cases AI is kind of part of computer
science so the main goal for NLP or
natural language processing is for
computers to understand and process
natural language in order to perform
tasks that are useful and in most cases
useful to us back as humans for instance
question answering of course the the
tricky bit is and the reason I put
understanding quotation marks is
computers don't really understand
language the way we understand language
there's a lot of you know linguistic
knowledge world knowledge and and the
connections to thought and planning and
you know love life and happiness and all
that that will make it very hard for a
computer to fully understand and
appreciate language so we're and there's
actually a lot of interesting stuff in
the philosophy of language too and you
can spend many many hours reading about
Frigga and victim Stein and a lot of
philosophy of language which we will not
do in this class it's very interesting
but in order to actually give you tools
to you know do what's possible now with
deep learning we kind of have to move
over that pretty quickly so we'll
basically take a very pragmatic approach
and look at a lot of tasks that are very
concrete and helpful to humans and in
some ways perfect language understanding
is so-called AI complete problem in the
sense that you kind of have to solve
almost all of other AI right I can talk
about planning I can talk about my motor
control in a robot I
talk about visual inputs and if you
really want to understand what the
meaning of greenness you know or blue
how do you really do that without seeing
the outside world and and so on so it's
a very complex problem and in many ways
we will simplify it
--- NLP levels ---
one thing that has
been it is pretty well established
inside NLP are different levels of
linguistic representation and skill and
so it starts with speech or in the case
of many computers who don't actually
have you know microphones or not
programmed to deal with speech with raw
text those could be pixely scans and in
PDF format or something in the case of
speech will then do phonetics or
phonology it's just the subfield that
deal it's basically we're trying to
understand speech and map it into a
system that humans can understand and
analyze and in the case of text we might
do optical character recognition and
tokenization just finding word do words
end and and start and this kind of you
know tokenization is pretty easy for
english right we just have spaces but
for other languages like Chinese you
might not know where specific word
starts or ends once you say all right I
have at least roughly the words that I
want to deal with you can then try to
understand and analyze these words and
that's the subfield of morphology and
again for linguists you might start
cringing here because any one of those
you know boxes could be its entire own
class right so we're doing a very very
bird's-eye view here of the field of NLP
and I'm I'm sorry to all the real
linguists in the room who who might
cringe now so morphology basically tries
to understand how words are constructed
you know if they're prefixes so I could
be it unfortunately so on would be a
prefix of the overall word unfortunately
for instance once you understand the
words and you know their meaning you in
general and sort of traditional NLP you
move on to syntactic analysis trying to
understand how words are put together so
I Can Has Cheezburger for instance does
not sound like a syntactically correct
phrase in the English language and
syntactic or syntax basically tells you
what is a reasonable syntactic phrase
how this grammar were
what is grammatical what is
ungrammatical and so on a lot of people
in traditional I know key would assume
that you need to have the morphological
and syntactic understanding order to go
to the next one but we'll actually see
that in some cases deep learning can
move straight into semantics
interpretations or semantics which
basically deals with trying to
understand the meaning of not just a
single words but also how they compose
into a complete sentence and once we
understand the meaning of a sentence
which is also a tricky bit and there are
lots of different definitions of what is
actually the meaning of a sentence once
we understand that we can maybe go to
discourse analysis or pragmatics which
tries to deal with and tries to
understand how multiple sentences from
the meaning of an entire story you know
a novel or a you know conversation
between people which can be very useful
once you want to have a phone agent or
something that can let you book a flight
ticket and wants to need to keep track
of the things you've said already in the
past we will mostly focus on syntactic
and semantic interpretations in the
class but there will be a little bit of
phonetics because and in phonology
because speech recognition has been
somewhat revolutionized by deep learning
so it's still part of NLP a lot of
people put speech into a little
subsection of four separate from NLP but
clearly speech is part of language
processing so mostly will focus on
semantic and syntactic interpretations
which are also the ones that are closer
to the real tasks that we might care
about so what what could those be that
any questions so far about the different
LP levels
just a head scratch alright
--- 9 (A tiny simple) NLP applications ---
so what our
NLP applications basically they range
from very very simple ones to extremely
complex systems that have you know
dozens or hundreds or even thousands of
PhDs work for multiple decades on so
some of the simple ones that we now
don't even consider artificial
intelligence anymore oftentimes we
define AI as the thing we cannot yet
quite do just like with chess we thought
Oh once we can play chess we have real
intelligence and then we play chess and
they're like oh it's just some branch
and bound search algorithm it's not
really AI and we will actually observe
that also in the class where things that
used to be considered amazing AI
technology are now kind of you know I
just talking to my phone and it's Syrian
that is not not AI anymore to some
people so so the simple simple tasks are
spell checking keyword search which is
what most search engines had worked on
in the past but now actually a lot of
them are moving closer and closer to
semantic analysis and harder tasks or
finding synonyms just setting up and you
know learning a thesaurus is a useful
task and helps people in in their
day-to-day lives next are sort of some
slightly more complex problems and many
of those will actually tackle in the
class and you'll be able to come up with
models or learn about models that can
solve many of those in that with the
same kind of model so we could for
instance try to extract specific types
of information from literature but also
from websites so you might want to find
all the prices of a product from some
free text or you might want to find the
dates and locations or people names or
company names in a large document
imagine you want to understand novel and
you want to find an algorithm that
creates a social network just from
reading a novel that is something that
you could do once you find all the
people and how close the people's names
are to each other
you can also classify text into really
anything and this is one of the very
sort of simple but also powerful ideas
if you have any kind of text and any
kind of label you can associate it with
it as long as people are able to
assign that label consistently you'll
probably be able to train an algorithm
to assign that label consistently as
well and that sounds kind of abstract
and boring until you realize oh boy
there are lots of interesting labels
that you can assign to a body of text
that could be you know reading levels of
school texts or it could be positive
negative sentiment of longer documents
and that might allow you to trade in a
automatic algorithmic trading algorithm
which is immensely useful for some
people and has some other problems and
then you come to the very very hard
tasks of machine translation where again
you kind of need to have a lot of world
knowledge linguistic knowledge
situational knowledge you need to keep
track of what has been said before and
so on so those are very hard tasks
similarly spoken dialogue systems or
real question answering where you don't
just do a search and then you find a
website that has the answer in it but
you actually get the answer so so those
are some super hard and you'll p
applications and will actually scratch a
little bit on those as well
so I mentioned NLP is very useful in
industry as well so obviously we all
know search and that has you know
modified a lot of or changed a lot of
our lives and in very nice way so we can
find information very quickly can be
written or spoken online advertisement
is also in some ways originally a very
simple tasks you just find a certain
keyword
you put ads right next to that but if
you actually have a better understanding
and you realize oh there's some
sentiment associated with it and you you
know they're complaining about this so
maybe you don't want to put your ad
right next to the one in the text that
says oh this product actually is really
bad because you know it's wasted money
to put the ad there you have automated
and I usually say assisted translation
if you have fully automated translation
you might get a hair salon that is
called could not connect to the
translator service so and that is a
particularly bad example but in other
cases you oftentimes the translation is
really raw it doesn't quite get the
subtleties so for instance if you
translate they were all pregnant into
French now in French there's a different
day for all male and all female or mixed
and so if you now say the male because
males are unfortunately still much more
in text so the algorithm will air and
decide of using the mail they in French
you'll say all those males were pregnant
and you know that doesn't work so it's
still in many cases just assisted
translation and not fully automated
similar the sentiment analysis is
getting better and better also partly
things to keep learning but it also has
its problems so here is an interesting
example from a couple of years ago where
Anne Hathaway starred in a movie and
then the movie reviews came out and they
were very positive
she acted really great and so on and
then immediately the stocks for the
company Berkshire Hathaway rose and so
you might think wow it's crazy they
really they start you're doing
algorithmic trading with these kinds of
algorithms and honestly if they had used
deep learning and had you know a little
bit better sense of entity
disambiguation they may have made a lot
more money and then speech recognition
is another task that can be seen as its
own sort of application in industry but
really it's connected to a lot of other
ones so translation and search and so on
so let's have one very very
oversimplified slide on why natural
language processing is actually hard so
I kind of alluded to this before but
there's really a huge amount of
complexity in representing and learning
automatically a lot of different types
of knowledge so we have linguistic
knowledge we know what grammar you know
what kinds of sentences give us you know
what kind of sentences are correct or
not
we have situational knowledge I know
that there are certain things I can say
in certain situations and not in others
we have a lot of world knowledge visual
knowledge that we might be referring to
and so on
so that is that is one of the examples
so here for instance let's let's assume
we try to build an algorithm that
understands who she is
in this sentence right here so this ends
this Jane hit June and then she fell so
now who is she
right well wait OOP June exactly and
then but now it's the sentences Jane had
June and then she ran so now you know
it's actually almost ambiguous ambiguous
again because it could be well you got
hidden and you want to run away or you
hit somebody and then you ran away so
again there's almost situational
knowledge but here you know it's more
likely to be Jane than June and it's in
some sense it's probabilistic but in the
first case it's very clear that it was
June and so being like how do we now
represent those that fact that we just
you know for us is very intuitive who
she is depending on on the verb how do
we instill that in an algorithm and that
will be one of the big questions and
we'll provide one so you should know
deep learning and it's not the only one
but it's actually one that that I think
moving forward is going to be very
powerful so so that is that is the first
large problem and then the second one is
ambiguity so here we have a sentence I
made her duck so who here has you know
an interpretation of what that could
mean rephrased yes exactly I made her a
duck and it tasted very good you know
exactly maybe in the end you have a
wooden duck or something so you made her
you carved one for her yeah exactly
like that and there's one there's a
fourth one dead uh yes
you what
like a master plan
interesting all right I did not think of
that one before there's one that s
actually very similar to the first one
which is you know I cook the duck for
her which could be I cooked the duck
that she owned so I actually made her
duck and not you know my other friends
stuff so lots of ambiguity right and you
can probably think of even more
all
right so that leads us maybe to deep
learning though there are some problems
here that I brought up that I don't know
if deep learning can solve it either yet
basically what is deep learning
it's a subfield of machine learning
hence the prerequisite of 2:29 being
very useful and to really appreciate the
difference between traditional machine
learning and deep learning we have to
kind of look at how does you know how
does traditional machine learning solve
some really hard tasks so let's take the
well semi-hard task of finding named
entities just identifying that you know
like Anne Hathaway is a person and
Berkshire Hathaway is a company for
instance we can look at traditional
systems that use for instance graphical
models like conditional random fields
and see how they actually solved that
task and what we observe then is that
really once you dig into it and you try
to improve the system or try to really
understand how it works you find that
the most important aspect of that isn't
the conditional random field that gives
you a sequence model on top it's really
the features that represent the decision
that represent sort of the input that we
give to a machine learning algorithm so
for named entity recognition for
instance we will look at the current
word the previous word in the next word
those are fairly straightforward and
then we might also look at character
engrams so you know if it's duck then
it's D you see you see K and and things
like that so character trigrams or by
Graham's
which just happens to be after a PhD
student looked at you know these kinds
of errors long enough found that that is
a useful feature that ran some
experiments that helped under
development set and so on you might want
to run a POS tagger so a part of speech
tagger that now it's a completely
separate system but you know oh you know
oftentimes named entities are nouns
so it clearly helps to have part of
speech so now you basically ran a
different machine learning system that
is also a sequence tagger on the whole
document and said alright this is a noun
as an adjective and so on so you know
not not ideal if you have to build now a
pipeline system that runs one system and
that first system is not modified by
what you want to do afterwards you might
look at the surrounding part of speech
sequences the word shape of the actual
word in question what is word shape it
basically tells you the capitalization
is the word all caps or just the first
letter or is it your daughter no
capitalized letters in the word and so
on and like I could go on so these are
just a subset of all the features that
in the end are in a system that now does
sort of professional state-of-the-art
level named entity recognition and so in
this kind of setting machine learning we
just becomes sort of it's reduced to
just optimizing the weights to make a
final prediction and the weights are oh
I think and you know this with this kind
of word shape all caps letters and the
next word being you know half the way or
something then this is the right this is
probably this kind of named entity so
really yeah this is kind of this is all
that machine learning does in that case
it has all these weights and it finds it
tries to optimize you know how important
is this feature in correlation in
connection with this feature and so on
so really when we look at machine
learning in practice we have these two
types we you know these two subtasks
which is first describe your data with
features that a computer can understand
you know a computer doesn't understand
that oh because she fell and she could
run away you know like and so on like
they don't have that knowledge we have
to somewhere somehow give it to them and
once we distilled all that then we give
it to our learning algorithm that just
computes the weights so really when we
talk about artificial intelligence and
for a very long time in the past it was
more human intelligence of PhD students
learning how to describe the features
how to describe these different tasks
and different problems and in the end
the learning algorithm was actually you
know just optimizing the weights so that
has in some ways you know
allowed us to make progress because it's
very hard to represent everything but
it's also what deep learning is trying
to overcome and in some ways deprecated
in a sense that the learning tries to do
the entire process so you just give it
raw input it learns what how to
represent that input and then it makes
also a final output so on a very high
level what does that look like and no
worries if you don't yet understand what
all these kinds of figures mean we'll
really very carefully and very slowly go
through those in the lecture not this
extra but you know throughout the
quarter so basically the idea of deep
learning is to do representation
learning when basically attempt to
automatically learn good features or
representations like the ones I just
mentioned for a named entity recognition
learning algorithms essentially attempt
to learn multiple levels of these kinds
of representations so you start with
ideally as raw of an input as possible
so just words for instance in the case
of natural language processing or and
that's kind of one of the fascinating
things in the case of computer vision a
lot of the same techniques that we'll
cover in this class actually also work
for computer vision and so there it
would be just the raw pixels so either
pixels or words or you know raw speech
signals and you give those and then you
piped them through a so called neural
network or a deep learning architecture
a model and in the end you get some
output in this case here the last layer
so because this lecture is recorded in
there lots of people online who will
probably say oh but you didn't mention
you know this person and this person's
you know impact on the field from from
twenty years ago I want to have one
slide on a little bit of the history of
the term and again it's grossly
oversimplified history here we could
have an entire history on deep learning
class so basically what we'll focus on
are different kinds of neural networks
neural networks you know are only one
type of deep learning there are actually
other probabilistic graphical models but
recently and especially for natural
language processing and neural networks
are the kinds of models that actually
work a lot better and they're faster to
train and and simpler to analyze
basically yeah it's become the de-facto
dominant model family inside the field
of deep learning you could be snarky and
say well really neural networks and deep
learning are just clever sort of
marketing terminology for what is
essentially stacked logistic regression
units so if you're familiar of logistic
regression in some way we could abstract
this entire class as just saying we put
a lot of logistic issues together so on
the other hand you know so this is
somewhat true but at the same time there
are a lot of interesting modeling
principles that come up when we try to
say oh we're learning the features we
try to transform our inputs we try to
understand how words compose and so on
and there are actually in some cases
interesting connections to neuroscience
especially in the visual case that we
don't cover very much so for NLP I will
personally stay away from making any
analogies to the brain I'm not a
neuroscientist that there are some
people actually in it Stanford - who do
think that there are very interesting
and important connections between deep
learning and neuroscience for us it will
be functions that we optimize and I'll
yeah
no no brain analogies for me moving
forward also and this is sort of just
yeah disclaimer I will not be taking a
historical approach here there are a lot
of techniques that have been invented in
the past and then have been somewhat
superseded and instead I will try to
just teach you the stuff that really
works well right now and in some cases I
mentioned that you know there's a
progression of ideas here and I will
point you to the papers that you know
you're definitely welcome to read but
we'll try to you know make it keep it as
current as possible if you're interested
in the history of deep learning there's
a great paper by your new youtuber and
keep learning in real networks and
overview so I'll just refer to that all
right so why why deep learning why do we
not use you know have a special class on
graphical models the natural language
processing which they're you know
there's a lot of work in that field to
basically
the manually designed features that are
often used in traditional machine
learning are often over specified
incomplete and take a long time to
design and validate right if you're a
PhD student you want to improve the
performance on your tasks in order to
publish a paper and improve you know
science and engineering you might have
to you know I have this idea you look at
your errors and then you you add another
extra feature to it and that's a very
slow process and in many cases and we'll
go through some examples it'll be you
know you've probably missed some things
because you can look at all the ways you
could possibly negate something all the
words that are possibly positive in the
world right now on the other hand the
features that will you will keep
learning our to keep learning algorithms
will cover in this class we'll be able
to learn are very easy to adapt you have
a different task just give that as an
input and all the intermediate
representations and features will be
learned so basically you've learning
will provide us also very flexible and I
would say almost universal or Universal
and learn about framework for
representing different kinds of
information or different kinds of
knowledge so I mentioned the world
knowledge there are ways we can
represent a bunch of facts in neural
networks
we'll have visual knowledge that you
know we can very easily connect to also
and as well as linguistic information
all right and what's also important is
we can do both unsupervised and
supervised learning so an unsupervised
learning we just give it a bunch of text
and it will actually learn how to
represent certain thing and actually be
able to extract information from just
you know all of Wikipedia without any
specific text at the same time I can say
this is a positive sentence find other
positive sentences and so it you know
that's also possible
a tiny historical approach to you know
what's relevant right now is you know in
many ways like I said deep learning
techniques go way back maybe starting in
the 60s and so you might ask well why
why now
why have we not had this class you know
ten years ago and so the the main reason
is that in 2006 these kinds of
techniques actually started to work so
they you know we're out there in theory
people had published papers on very
small data sets of like ten sentences
and they kind of had some interesting
patterns at least in the case of NLP but
really now after 2006 and then really
picking up in the last five years they
started to work incredibly well and
sometimes better than systems that
hundreds and thousands of researchers
have worked on before the three main
reasons for that is that deep learning
techniques benefit a lot from having
more data and something that if you're
still familiar with 2:29 you will
appreciate it imagine you had a
classification problem and you wanted to
classify any element from this class
versus elements from that class and now
if you had a very simple model a linear
model like logistic regression you could
only have you know you'd say everything
on this side is in class one and
everything on the other side is in class
two now deep learning will actually
allow us to learn much more complex
decision boundaries and no worries we'll
go through all of these things here in
detail but it might actually be able to
learn that this is potentially the
better decision boundary and if we have
a lot of data then this might actually
you know be a much better one that will
in the end generalize better so if you
now have an example here for instance
whereas the previous simple linear
decision boundary would have gotten that
not gotten that right a deep learning
model would have gotten gotten it right
so basically deep learning can benefit a
lot more from
more data it's a very powerful model
family
it'll also actually benefit a lot from
faster machines and CPUs and GPUs so
your graphics cards from gaming actually
has now transformed the company Nvidia
that used to build these mostly for
gaming and now they're really interested
in excited about deep learning deep
learning in the end will boil down to a
lot of matrix multiplications and it
turns out those can be very easily
paralyzed so again a big advantage and
also moving forward I think you know
there will be even more multi-core
processing systems so it'll benefit even
more and lastly and that is kind of the
most interesting part to me personally
and also the one that will cover most in
the classes there are actually a lot of
new models new optimization algorithms
and ideas that have you know come up in
the last couple of years are any
questions so far
all right I guess I'm either being very
clear or everybody has a food coma all
right so let's look at two of the
breakthroughs of deep learning and how
you know why why there was such a high
impact so the first huge breakthrough
result of deep learning came for large
scale and large datasets speech
recognition so where traditional
features had got new specific word error
rate in an acoustic model that basically
is given some new acoustic features and
tries to predict a phoneme or a word
from that deep learning by somebody who
wasn't traditionally an expert in speech
recognition he had not done previous
work actually a friend of mine George
Dahl he was able to get a 33% reduction
in error in terms of the word error rate
compared to traditional human design
features so every time you now speak
into your phone your Android or your
Microsoft phone or whatever or your
iPhone there is a deep learning system
behind that that will try to understand
your speech
the second huge breakthrough and we'll
actually talk about the speech more in
subsequent lectures the the second big
breakthrough which we won't be able to
cover in this class were came in
computer vision in 2012 were basically
until then most of the large deep
learning groups had to spend most of the
time on speech and computer vision and
so the big breakthrough paper here by
Alex Khrushchev ski from 2012 was
imagenet classification with deep
convolutional neural networks and so
unlike before you can now literally as
easy as drag and drop
classified different kinds of images
it's it's become very very easy to use
this technology instead of just saying
this is you know a dog versus a house or
you know the a bird versus a national
park that you can actually find all
different kinds of birds and so on and
here are also some very interesting
connections to neuroscience and and so
the visual cortex and what it does as
you learn more abstract layers in neural
networks and don't worry if you don't
understand all the details here but
basically in the first layer of of these
kind of visual
deep learning algorithms you'll capture
just very simple edges you know there
are lots of crooked edges or straight
ones and so on and different color
features and as you move higher and
higher in the architecture you'll find
more complex shapes so maybe here you
have some you know half circles and
different color gradients and so on and
then as you move to the next layer you
might find specific features for wheels
or certain types of fruits and so on
alright so that was a very very quick
and oversimplified introduction to deep
learning and again you know that is what
we'll cover a lot more of throughout
this lecture so basically when we say
deep learning NLP it's sort of long word
so we'll just refer to that in the
future as a deep NLP and basically we're
combining the ideas and goals of NLP and
use representation learning and deep
learning to actually solve a lot of
different kinds of problems and
basically there have been several big
improvements in recent years across
various different NLP levels so speech
morphology syntax and semantics as well
as applications and so in the last part
of this lecture we'll actually go
through a couple of these and that will
you know make it a little less terse on
your NLP background knowledge but you
don't really have to you know memorize
the IPA table like you would in a
phonology class so let's look and in the
next couple of slides on different
levels of representation in traditional
linguistics and NLP versus deep learning
and then look at how those actually
affect real applications so in phonology
what a linguists might come up with is
different ways of categorizing different
phonemes so we have for instance
fricatives like that or closest so like
basically they try to come up and
realize all the ways that your speech
apparatus can create different kinds of
sounds
and in many cases and we'll observe this
in in the future deep learning actually
uses some of the ideas from traditional
linguistics but only as a final output
label internally they will represent all
these different sounds as simply vectors
so vectors as literally just a list of
numbers all right so let's assume we're
able to find phonemes
in in texts or in speech the next step
was morphology and so in traditional
morphology you might analyze a word like
uninterested in you know terms of its
prefix stem and suffix and the sort of
not quite magic but you know initially
it might feel like magic in for deep
learning again every morpheme will be a
vector so just a list of numbers and
will actually be able to train a neural
network that will combine two vectors
into one vector and really we'll we'll
describe all this and in a lot of
details throughout this lecture but you
know you just say on is a list of
numbers fortunate is a list of numbers
and unfortunate now combines to another
list of numbers and ideally that list of
numbers will somehow capture as much
information as possible so just to give
you a very rough sense of what is
actually captured in these vectors we
can actually project them down using
something like PCA into a lower
dimensional two dimensional vector space
so we can actually visualize and see
what's going on inside these numbers
that we now just learned based on
predicting something and so what we'll
observe and I'll zoom in in a second is
that will actually have similar
linguistic structures emerging by by
itself from deep learning models so all
the words in this area of the projective
vector space here will actually be
announced so let's zoom into this and
what we notice afterwards is where the
large areas of the vector space are are
just part of speech tags once you zoom
in you actually have semantic
substructure so the model and deep
learning models that we'll cover in this
class and actually start with this
Wednesday will actually capture the fact
that France and Germany are somewhat
more similar to each other
then you know Britain and China for
instance and in other parts of the space
you may have a lot of verbs and you can
see up Soleri verbs for instance where
linguists would say oh I think you know
is where was an our our auxiliary verbs
it just learns to automatically cluster
them and group them together alright so
that is basically the way we represent
morphology and word information is just
a list of numbers a vector well let's
move on to the next level which is
syntax basically the traditional
representation of syntax and again I've
actually personally taken like three
different class or four actually on
syntax so it this again is only a very
very bird's eye view and one example
picked out from all of syntactic theory
there's a lot more to all of this but
one traditional way to represent
syntactic categories is just in in terms
of discrete phrase structures so you
might say you know there's a noun phrase
like the house or a verb phrase like is
read so is is a verb read is an
adjective
together they become a verb phrase and
you may have recursive structure in here
where you may have a noun phrase inside
another noun phrase so you might say the
house at the end of the street is red so
now the street is a noun phrase but off
the street is a prepositional phrase
where that starts with the preposition
off and so you may ask 10 linguists to
come up with a tree structure and in
many cases they may actually come up
with different ones so that's it's a
it's tricky because we use language and
it's a very fluid system and sometimes
you start making mistakes and then if
enough people make those mistakes they
actually become the de facto standard
and then you know so things things are
very fluid things that might have been
wrong in English 100 years ago now are
totally acceptable and so yeah discrete
categories that's that's the main idea
and now in deep learning we could
actually use the idea of having free
structures but instead of saying this is
a specific noun phrase or a
prepositional phrase maybe we'll just
say it's a vector
we have already vectors describing words
now we'll train neural networks to
basically take in two to word vectors
and produce a phrase vector and this is
kind of it's kind of crazy when you
think about it right we're now trying to
represent an arbitrarily long phrase of
multiple words maybe it's just one word
maybe it's ten words maybe it's 25 words
and just a list of numbers
all right so in throughout this class
we'll have to very carefully analyze how
many numbers are enough yeah you know
what is actually being represented in
those numbers are similar phrases now
close to each other in the vector space
or not there's a lot of a lot of
interesting questions that we can ask
once we actually try to attempt this any
questions yes
that's a great question so the question
is am i putting these more vectors into
the network or not will actually will
cover word vectors because they're kind
of the first building block for a lot of
the other subsequent models that we work
on in the next two lectures and to
answer is that we actually often have a
model that learns word vectors in
unsupervised way and then we take them
and we plug them into another system
like a sentiment analysis algorithm for
instance yes
sorry sagen
oh is it the you clean this so there
will actually be a lot of different
kinds of distance metrics that we can
use to define similarity and vector
space could be cosine distance Euclidean
distance simple inner products and so on
so we'll go a little bit into that as
well
is there a way to standardize different
representations of the training data
image so yeah so did I mention that's a
good question so a lot of cases a lot of
experiments that will run the question
how many dimensions are enough will come
up and in fact in your problem sets you
will have to run cross-validation
experiments you'll have to try maybe 10
is enough for this really simple task
maybe I need 50 maybe for a very complex
large document classification task I
would need more but sometimes the longer
the document is that actually is simpler
the problem becomes so if you want to
understand sentiment for instance and
you have a thousand words to go off of
well if you see awesome and wonderful
and family and good times and so on
multiple times they'll actually become
quite straightforward that it's a
positive one but if you see only a
single sentence and you might say this
was not the most awesome movie then it
becomes harder because Yuri need to
understand the one meaning of the knot
to get that sentence right so it'll
actually depend on the task
great question all right so the last and
I think most interesting representation
there or you know layer of level of
natural language processing is semantics
and again semantics very complex field
lots of connections to the philosophy of
language you could take at least two
very very interesting lectures on just
semantics one way to represent semantics
is lambda calculus and I'm going to try
to explain to you this expression right
here but don't worry we'll actually not
use those kinds of representations
throughout the rest of the class so no
worries if you don't really understand
that and can follow basically you assume
that certain words are very carefully in
human design functions so you have that
take as input other functions so for
instance likes you might say is a
function that takes as input an object
entity and then that creates another
function that now requires a subject
entity and in the end produces the
overall sentence representation likes
MSM for Mary and Esther sue so
that has some problems right one what if
somebody said liked now you need to have
this different representation or maybe
the same for for that also that kind of
discrete representation doesn't allow
you to now capture similarity or some of
the fuzziness that we have in language
so there's no connection between likes
and liked right you would then have to
say well those are just two completely
separate types of words and you kind of
stuck again with how do you make a
computer understand that likes and liked
and maybe enjoying to hang out with are
actually roughly similar so basically
there's no notion here of similarity and
you have these discrete representations
and now you probably are starting to be
able to guess it
but for deep learning every word every
phrase from last slide and every single
logical expression that compares
different sentences will also just be a
vector and at this point if you're a
critical mind you should start wondering
if that is actually the right thing to
do right logic is a very discrete kind
of endeavor right it's either true or
false
this element is a you know either in
this set or it's not in this set and so
if you think about this this will kind
of blow your mind right it's it
basically will say the sentence all
reptiles walk and some turtles move and
everything here is a vector reptiles is
a vector to phrase for all reptiles is a
vector all reptiles walk is a vector and
now the comparison of all reptiles walk
and some turtles move can be classified
in the end as the so called entailment
relationship if all reptiles walk then
clearly the some turtles also move so
one logically follows from the other and
the crazy thing is deep learning can
actually capture that they can actually
learn these kinds of logical
representations and that is something
that was very unintuitive to a lot of
people working in the field of NLP
any questions so far all right so let's
move on to some of the applications that
you will be able to program throughout
this class and and that are exciting to
work on so the first one is sentiment
analysis and I just want to again sort
of show you the difference between the
traditional approach here and how deep
learning we'll deal with this
traditionally you may have curated
sentiment dictionaries that come you
know are combined with some kind of bag
of words representation so you might
just say if I want to find if this new
document here is positive or negative I
will look into my list of positive words
that I came up with like awesome
wonderful and great and so on and if
whenever I find a word from that list
that an expert created I will say that's
a positive you know
+1 for positive but of course you know
there will be tricky sentences like
badass or awesome or you know where it's
other words that you might come up with
now that an expert you know five years
ago or 10 years ago may not have put
into their list of positive words and so
that is that is one one problem here
with with traditional sentiment analysis
and then a so-called bag of words
representation and we'll just say does
this word appear in the document or not
and we'll look at these more in the
future but basically that will never
allow you to capture word order and so
if you you know say Jane loves john or
john loves jane it would be the same if
you had a bag of words representation
and that can be problematic for
capturing some sentiment next you might
say all right well just looking at
positive and negative words wasn't
enough now I want to create negation
features so whenever I see not in front
of something positive I will say it
flips entirely and becomes negative
which is not quite true either and you
might think that you might say my
intuition about sentiment analysis might
tell me that that's negative but it's
not quite true so if you say for
instance the movie was not awesome but
it was pretty good you know it's still
roughly on the positive side so it's not
like negation always flips to sentiment
perfectly right and so and at the same
time you know there will be a slang
language you know
and gonna capture everything basically
like the kinds of negative negation
features that you might come up with
might not be exhaustive for describing
the full space now here's here's one
cool result which is the same deep
learning model and one that we'll go
over in this class that was used for the
morphology analysis or the same model
was used for the morphology analysis I
just described the syntactic analysis
the logical semantics and now sentiment
it's the same and in this case it's
called a recursive neural network and
section one that I worked on a lot
during my PhD it's the same kind of
network is allows you to solve these
different tasks allows you to represent
different levels of linguistics all in
vector spaces so it's a very very
powerful tool and so we can kind of look
at what this what this looks like in
practice so here's a demo from one of my
old papers from two years ago and here
we can come up with the sentence that
would in most traditional NLP systems
would have been misclassified is
positive the sentence is this movie
doesn't care about cleverness wit or any
other kind of intelligent humor in a
traditional system you might say well
it's got humor intelligent kind with
cleverness care how negative could it be
right
but then there's one little dozen in
front of it and that doesn't have a so
has a so-called scope over the entire
rest of the sentence so when you send
that to a system what it will do is
basically give you this analysis so
realize intelligent humor is indeed
something positive and any other kind is
and cleverness and wit are positive and
you know care here it actually makes a
mistake it's thinks it's neutral but you
can see here a probability distribution
and still realizes there's a lot of
positive sentiment in here and once it
realizes that doesn't care about it then
it flips then flips it and makes
actually makes it negative and again we
did not have to program Oh doesn't plus
something positive becomes negative
right it just learned it from a lot of
examples so we could actually see
here this movie I know didn't care and
you know it's still negative or it does
care a lot
and now it even realizes that you know
caring a lot actually does is positive
all the way so you can play around with
this demo yourself and a lot of people
have and you know obviously it's I have
lots of people commented on into it or
some funny things in there it's the
internet so I tried to not not the
censor it but uh so yeah so you can
basically learn a lot of interesting
facts from this and and play around with
it and see where does it break right you
can be very very sarcastic or some
people put in like this movie is not not
not not not not good right and then you
know they're like oh it should flip
every time but that's also not how
humans would use that right if you said
this was no no no no no no not good
nobody keeps track and like flips the
sentiment right it's just a really
strong not so you know depends yes great
question so we will go through all of
those in all the gory details and
ideally in the end you can reimplemented
self and have an gain an intuition
oftentimes when you work on these
projects the very first time you
implement your own the learning
algorithm you you have no idea should I
have 25 or 500 dimensions and very
quickly after two or three hopefully
programming and problem sets you'll gain
some intuition and that can go all the
way to if you work on it for a couple of
years you get into the unfortunate
situation where the very first guess
that you've had is actually so good that
running proper cross-validation doesn't
improve it anymore so that that is
actually the downside of that so in this
case we only need it around 30 or so
dimensions for every for representing
every phrase and and and every word and
this model actually is a single layer
model but it's a different type of layer
and one that we'll cover in the lecture
2 it's a tensor layer so instead of
having a standard sort of matrix
multiplication this is going a little
bit into too many details don't worry if
you don't understand that yet but if you
have a tensor you have a much more
powerful interaction so it's a different
type of neural network
um in this case like sentiment analysis
does is the training set have to be
annotated yes yeah so this is a good
example where you really want to have a
lot of annotations so I guess to answer
your other part here you had to have
10,000 labeled sentences and these were
labeled both on the phrase level and the
sentence level alright so let's move to
the last two tasks of today which are
also the hardest ones and in some ways
are the most amazing ones so question
answering is is one of the hardest tasks
in NLP and it basically in the past has
required a lot of feature engineering to
capture a lot of different world
knowledge and other types of knowledge
so you know in again question answering
you might want to ask you know who built
the Taj Mahal or who you know
constructed the Eiffel Tower or
something and so what originally you
would have done is you know is the view
asks like is the main verb a certain
trigger and if it is then look for a
certain regular expression and a certain
WH word that exactly tries to you know
find these kinds of types of agents or a
specific type of theme and again for
deep learning we can actually use the
exact same neural network architecture
that we use from a faulty syntax logics
and and sentiment to try to do question
answering and what's kind of amazing is
a missing the citation here this is a
paper from a year in Maryland the
amazing thing is when we learn it when
we learn these kinds of models for
question answering it will actually
capture that Ronald Reagan and Jimmy
Carter for instance are quite similar
kinds of entities you know there are
both presidents in a certain time span
or you know Thomas Jefferson here in
George Washington it will just learn to
project these somewhere into the space
it will deal with all the gory details
that we would otherwise have to think
about for decades on how do we represent
the fact that they're both presidents
but one sort of in an early time and was
in War of Independence and so on it'll
just push that somewhere into the vector
space and deal with that problem for you
of course that has the one big downside
is you can't tell it any more where you
want you might say well I have this one
specific extra fact that to me
personally makes it very different I
want it I want that number to be
different you can't do these things
anymore all right so you lose a little
bit of the freedom but at the same time
the model actually is able to store
these facts in a way that makes the
gives you the best performance for the
task in question and so this specific
model actually is able to compete in a
quiz bowl trivia competition challenge
it actually beats a couple of human
players so you know just to give you an
idea of how how crazy that is
right you you have Watson the system
that won jeopardy against the world's
experts of expert players that was a
gigantic very complex system that
required a supercomputer to run and has
access to all of Wikipedia and can look
up tons of things and it had you know
many many millions of dollars being
being spent on it in order to get a good
performance and now one grad student was
able to build a system using deep
learning technology to also build a
question-answering system so this is why
you know this is such a useful skill for
you to acquire it's it's a very very
powerful tool all right so the last last
application for today machine
translation basically again there are
lots of different levels that you can
use for translation you can try to do a
direct translation from you know words
in this language towards in that
language just look up in a dictionary
and so on but of course that will never
give you a very good translation because
many there's it's usually an end to end
mapping right one word can mean lots of
different things in another language so
then you know and this is again these
are progressions here over decades and
and hundreds of PhD students and or
probably even thousands in the case of
of machine translation that that have
been worked through so you might have
syntactic transfer you look at certain
phrases and if I have a very large
corpus these are all trained on parallel
corpora so you have you know here's a
paragraph of you know the European
Parliament paragraph description in
German here's one in English and one in
French or an Italian and so on and you
might say well that particular phrase
not just the word but that phrase often
corkers with that other phrase in the
other language
and then you know basically you can
parse and try to translate whole phrases
and then sometimes you see the whole
sentence and maybe you can try to
translate the whole sentence right away
that is the next level and then you can
use the semantic level and say well
sometimes I describe this in lot in
terms of logic you know X made Y happy
and now I have this interlingua the sort
of language between the languages that
abstracts away from all the complexities
and subtleties of
each language and has one general
description which is also very very hard
if you know like different cultures and
so on and you might say okay I will
translate everything into this logical
or very discrete semantic representation
and then I will just generate a surface
form a specific way to describe that so
what do people think is the inter lingua
for deep learning exactly it's vectors
and so this is a very recent result from
just last year they're actually a couple
of groups that are starting now to use
deep learning for machine translation
but basically the crazy result here is
we could literally take word vectors we
squeeze them through a very deep very
powerful deep learning architecture and
we take the entire sentence and we just
describe it in terms of one vector and
we have another neural network that just
says now translate that vector from the
previous language into the other
language and it kind of works its I mean
this system is not yet as good as the
system that you know Google has built
over the last ten years and you know
with many many millions of you know
dollars and lots of brainpower but in
you know just one year one group of deep
learning experts could build a system
that is actually very competitive and if
you can do that so quickly it's only a
matter of time I think
but again I'm optimistic and slightly
biased that it will outperform human
systems because unlike for sentiment it
is basically impossible to describe all
the features for machine translation by
hand right you can have no no set of
people could do that it changes over
time it's incredibly complex we
you can do that in fact some people I
mean you could do that with any system
and it just gets worse and worse and at
some point it's so ridiculous I think
there's a video on YouTube where people
translate the song song lyrics like five
times through a translation system and
it just comes out pretty much garbage
but um it's possible alright so this was
today's first lecture very high level
very bird's-eye view in the next lecture
we'll actually look at the first and
most important representation that all
these different models start from which
is work vectors and we'll see that these
models capture lots of interesting facts
about them thank you