ninth lecture of CS 224 d today we'll
talk about recursive neural networks I
have a somewhat personally relationship
with these since I've worked a lot of
these kinds of models during my PhD
---------------------------------------- 2(2) Overview
so
we'll actually spend two lectures on
these just like recurrent neural
networks are pretty important they're
very flexible kinds of models and so
basically today will motivate them a
little bit with so called
compositionality meaning you know a sort
of technique to get to the meaning of
longer phrases and then we'll actually
look at a slightly different kind of
objective function a structure
prediction kind of objective function
today and back propagation through
structure is really going to be very
similar to back propagation which you
already know with just three you know
slight modifications and then the nice
thing is that these models are very
general and so if we have enough time at
the end we can also actually have you
know two or three slides on a computer
vision example turns out the exact same
model will work for images as well and
then in the next lecture we can go and
look into a couple of modifications
couple of extensions to the standard
recursive neural networks when I mention
RNN today it will be mostly recursive
neural networks it's unfortunate because
our nents and the last couple of
lectures were a recurrent neural
networks and we'll actually look into
the difference between those two as well
--------------------------------------------- 3 (11) Building on Word Vector Space Models
all right so we're very familiar by now
with word vector space models where you
know words that are similar in meaning
and have similar kinds of part of speech
tags are close by so all the nouns are
clustered together and inside the non
cluster would have you know different
semantic sub structures so the vector of
germany would be closer to the vector of
France for instance and Monday and
Tuesday will be closer to one another
but of course words never appear in
isolation and so so far we haven't
really thought about what happens to
vector representations when we want to
represent specific short sub phrases so
what if I have the two phrases the
country of my birth and the place where
I was born for instance if I was to
build a text summarization system
clearly I wouldn't want to have both of
these together despite
you know country in place not being that
similar and birth as a you know noun and
where I was born as a verb but ideally
if we build a sex organization system we
wouldn't include both of these phrases
right and so the question is how should
we represent the meaning of these longer
phrases and the answer that is similar
you know to or the answer will basically
give to that today is by mapping those
phrases into the exact same vector space
where we had words
--------------------------------------- 4 (12) Semantic Vector Spaces
and so just to give
you a sort of broader sense of where
that puts us there are a lot of these
representations for single word vectors
we look through word Tyvek and and Club
vectors basically they're sort of
distributed and distributional
techniques it's actually a lot of other
ones such as brown clusters which we're
not going to cover much in this class
but basically they also capture core
current statistics and so they are great
but they really can capture longer
phrases and then there are a lot of
other models that are very widely used
such as bag of words models or the PCA
based models that we discovered for
document representations and those are
reasonably good for information
retrieval we just want to find you know
specific documents of mention specific
phrases or document exploration we just
want to know these documents roughly
about politics or sports or things like
that but of course they ignore the word
order and so we can't really get too
detailed understanding inside our
representation and so today we'll look
at another technique for finding vectors
that really represent phrases and
sentences without ignoring word order
and actually trying to capture both the
syntactic structure as well as the
semantic information of those phrases
-------------------------------------------- 5 (13) How should we map phrases into a vector space?
so
that leads us to the question of how we
should go about doing this and in this
lecture we'll introduce and use the
principle of compositionality which in
our case states that the meaning vector
of a sentence is determined by one the
meaning of its words the word vectors
and throughout the lecture I will
describe those you know I straight those
in two dimensions but of course there
will generally be you know 21
to 300 dimensional so much larger
dimensional and to the rules that are
used to combine them and unlike before
where we just go from left to right and
we just compute one vector for
everything that we've read so far from
the left side this time we'll actually
adhere to the grammatical structure of
the sentence and we'll try to find
specific noun phrases that go together
so for instance my birth is by itself a
reasonably grammatical or syntactic
phrase and similarly the country is a
noun phrase and so we can combine those
two and then of my birth is actually a
prepositional phrase so those you know
the word vector of off will be combined
with the word vector of my birth and so
on and then ideally at the end of it
the final resulting vector will actually
be somewhere close to other countries in
a single word vector space and so the
neat thing about these models today is
that they basically can jointly learn
these so-called parse trees and
compositional vector representations
that ideally captures syntactic and
semantic information of the phrases
underneath them and not of the entire
context that we've had so far to the
left
------------------------------------- 6 (14) Sentence Parsing: What we want
so what is what is sentence parsing
what when we say we want to parse a
sentence what do we actually want out of
it so let's assume we start with a
sentence like the cat sat on the mat
very simple phrase what were sentence
what we would want is to have a model
that understands that the cat is a
proper noun phrase and I could now
replace that noun phrase with any other
noun phrase and it would still be a
grammatical English sentence so I could
say the car sat on the mat or you know
the whole class sat on the mat like any
kind of noun phrase could now be
replaced with this one and it would
still be a grammatical sentence
similarly the mat is a noun phrase and
now on the mat is a prepositional phrase
and again we could replace that
prepositional phrase with any other one
and still get a syntactically or
grammatically plausible English sentence
so we could say the cat sat you know
beyond the scope of this lecture you
know
that doesn't make any semantic sense but
is actually a grammatically correct
sentence and that is that is a big an
important distinction right grammar
doesn't tell you that much about
semantics and then to sit on the math as
a verb phrase and together this whole
thing is a sentence that is sort of the
standard way of defining the parsing
tasks we get these discrete tree
structures and they're different
depending on the input
------------------------------------------- 8 (15) Learn Structure and Representation
of course where
we will want is not just having this
discrete structures but ideally we want
to have again everything represented as
a vector and so we'll actually look into
how we can compute these vector
representations that now represent any
specific sub phrase without the context
------------------------------------------------ 8 (16) Learn Structure and Representation?
and so the first question we have to ask
ourselves here is do we really need
these structures you know we're saying
we learn structure and representation
but reading the last couple of lectures
we've also learned some kind of
structure and representation it just
happened to be that that representation
was always everything to the left of you
know what do what the current word is
-------------------------------------------- 9 (17) Sidenote: Recursive vs recurrent neural networks
and so that leads us to three slides of
the side note of you know should we use
these recursive structures the tree
structures or just change structures and
this could be a very lengthy argument
I'm going to try to distill it in in
just three three slides but basically
the main difference here is that you
know chains are actually special types
of trees right they just happen to
always branch in one direction all right
so from general graph theory you know
that changes are special types of trees
and so in that sense the recursive ones
are just generalizations of recurrent
ones and the default could be to just
say well I just take all the words and
instead of looking at their grammar I
just combine them one at a time right
and so you can see this as you know when
you have these specific words you could
just say you know I keep combining them
one word to the right all right and that
is also tree it just happens to
be able to flatten it out and call it a
chain all rights in that sense they're
actually not that different
------------------------------------------------- 10 (18) Sidenote: Are languages recursive?
however the question is sort of then is
language a recursive kind of thing and
so there's a long history here of papers
and I don't think it's yet clear whether
this is cognitively plausible like do
people really put together specific
phrases in their brains and so on and
fortunately we're not cognitive science
class right now so we can kind of put
that on the table and say well maybe
maybe not but recursion is clearly
helpful in describing natural language
it is very helpful to say for instance
that you know the church which has nice
windows the church which has nice
windows is a noun phrase I can replace
that noun phrase with another noun
phrase they've got a grammatical
sentence and yet inside that noun phrase
we have a relative clause which has nice
windows and that itself also contains a
noun phrase namely the nice windows and
so that from just describing language is
clearly very useful and now there are
basically four arguments of you know
that we use for now and basically say it
is just kind of helpful for a lot of
different tasks that we encounter in
natural language processing
one of those is disambiguation so here I
show you the first two parse trees that
look a little more realistic something
you would actually see when you parse
the sentence and you see here the the
sentence you need read them from the
left to right so here he eats spaghetti
with a spoon and the other sentences he
eats spaghetti with meat now what this
tells us here is basically we have PE
which is a personal pronoun and personal
pronouns are noun phrases so far so good
we have verb phrase this year and now
the entirety of that sentence eats
spaghetti or that phrase eat spaghetti
with a spoon is a verb phrase eats is
the verb now spaghetti is a plural noun
and now this is the interesting part
here this is a so-called PP or a
prepositional phrase and this overall
problem here is a PP attached
ambiguity so if a computer was to read
the sentence and you know reads he eats
spaghetti with a spoon versus he eats
spaghetti with meat now how can we know
whether the computer understands that
when I say with a spoon I actually mean
that I modify the way I eat the
spaghetti as in this PP should attach to
the verb phrase versus I say he'd
spaghetti with meat whereas this with
which also just has some noun phrase
inside of it this PP actually attaches
to the type of spaghetti because we're
not modifying how we were modifying what
we'd alright so if we have this kind of
structure and we make this explicit it
will be useful to disambiguate these two
cases and now the model could actually
you know tell us whether it got it right
and you know we can do downstream tasks
now and also query for instance the
model and ask give me all the different
ways somebody could eat spaghetti
alright maybe you did it with a fork
maybe you do a fork and a spoon and so
on
--------------------------------------------------- 11 (19) Is recursion useful?
are there any questions about this
part state you again yeah so back in
undergrad I actually took two entire
semesters of just syntax and grammar
theory and things like that and so again
this is like an insane
oversimplification here could literally
spend an entire year just talking about
all the subtleties of how these trees
are created so a bit of a cognitive
overload in some ways
so the question is are they really
useful for sort of semantic
understanding versus just grammatical
understanding and the answer here is in
some ways both and a lot of linguists
postulate that in order to understand
the sentence you first understand the
words then you understand how words are
put together and then you know you get
to the actual meaning of that sentence
and you understand you get to the
meaning through the structure first and
some people say well maybe not all right
so this is this is a very much up for
debate clearly here we see you know a
noun phrase well there's no there's no
noun phrase here inside another noun
phrase but here here that is the case
right with meat the meat is a noun
phrase in the spaghetti so we did
understand more about grammatical
structure here and certainly if we were
to for instance train whether students
are using correct grammar this seems
like clearly a very useful model however
we also got some better understanding of
what the model actually understood here
when it read those sentences right so
eating spaghetti with a spoon and now
here the model understood that with the
Spooner you know understood rotation
marks understood that with the spoon
here actually attaches to the verb
phrase and hence it modifies how you eat
the spaghetti so we did gain both
syntactic and semantic understanding of
this in yes
individual earning offices
so I did not what is the difference
between what
that's a great question well we'll
actually get to that a little bit
throughout the lecture
--------------------------------------------------- 11 (19) -------------------------------
so the the next
three reasons are sort of you know let's
say recursive structure cognitively
questionable but clearly useful as a way
to describe language now it's also
useful for just real tasks so let's say
we wanted to for instance do somewhat
complex co-reference analysis where and
koreff what we basically want to
understand is when you refer today or it
what did you actually mean when you when
you say that right and it usually means
you have some anaphora for instance so
here's here's an example john and jane
went to a big festival they enjoyed the
trip and the music there now
co-reference resolution would be the
task of understanding who is they when I
actually mentioned that you know this
day right here and in this case here
would be John and Jane so now we want to
refer to that entire phrase now when I
say they enjoy the trip and I ask what
do you mean by the trip then ideally you
would say well the trip meant they went
to a festival right and so now going to
a festival is a specific type of trip
and it's not that Jane and John went to
the big festival is the specific type of
trip it's just you know going to a
festival so you might want to refer to
just that and now somebody else could
have that same trip and you know you can
refer to that as one coherent unit and
now there would be potentially you know
the big festival maybe there are two
festivals a big one in small one they
went to one not the other now you go
basically there so this year basically
we've seen a couple of times we could
also refer to just her and just him for
instance just Jane and just John and in
both cases we wouldn't want to have only
a representation for everything that was
you know read until now right we would
only want to have something we can refer
to that is a sub phrase in that sentence
third reason is that the labeling
sometimes becomes less clear so if we if
we basically only have a single label at
each word so here we have a sentence
such as I like the bride
strean but not the buggy slow keyboard
of the phone now ideally we could just
classify buggy so keyboard of the phone
or buggy slow keyboard by itself as an
entity and that is negative whereas
something before here is positive right
and we don't necessarily just want to
classify the entire sentence here or
this entire paragraph but we ideally
understand you know each of these sub
phrases and they can have different
kinds of labels if we were to classify
sentiment for instance and again here it
is an interesting co-reference problem
it was a pain to type with or it was
nice to look at depending on what the
information here is the semantics of
what's following the it it's actually
you know either referring to the screen
or the keyboard so this is the task of
coroner's resolution it's actually kind
of an interesting task and NLP alright
and then the last argument is somewhat
of a pragmatic argument which is in some
tasks it just works better to use these
grammatical structures but this is also
an ongoing field of research so maybe
eventually we'll find that we could get
away which is some very very deep lsdm
model and we don't need them at all and
maybe whenever you have a phrase you can
kind of have some neurons that kind of
just capture now as a phrase and then
the forget GAE turns on and and they are
the next layer will kind of deal with
this thing it's it's still up for debate
and it's a very active area of research
but okay let's for now assume and it's
still the case that on some tasks these
models work the best right now on some
standard benchmark data sets
------------------------------------- 12 (20) Recursive Neural Networks for Structure Prediction
and so
let's define actually what a recursive
neural network is and how we get these
parse tree structures so basically we'll
have two inputs which are in general the
candidate children's representations so
in the beginning those will just be the
words for instance the and mat and then
later on it could be you know
representations of freight phrase
vectors that actually already were
computed before and the output in the
first kind of example where we actually
look at how to compute the tree
structure will be two things the first
one is the semantic representation if we
merge these two nodes
and the second one will be a score of
how plausible the new node would be so
ideally here again we'll compute a score
--------------------------------------------------- 13 (21) Recursive Neural Network Definition
that will say this is a reasonable
syntactic phrase and we want to increase
that score if it was actually true and
we want to decrease it if it's some
random ungrammatical phrase so what is
what are the equations for this model
here well it's a very simple one the
first thing we do here is we just
concatenate c1 and c2 the children the
left child and the right child of each
node in the tree we concatenate them and
then we multiply them by this matrix W
here and now the parent vector P should
have the same dimensionality as each of
the single children so let me ask you
what should the dimensionality now of W
be let's say c1 and c2 each one is n
dimensional it's an N dimensional vector
now what should the dimensionality of W
be
say louder yes exactly and bite to it
and so to understand this a little bit
we can also write this in a different
way we could instead of writing W times
c1 and c2 we could rewrite this and say
well W is a block w1 w2 so like we said
this is an R and by 2n matrix and this
matrix will be exactly this and we have
here C 1 and C 2 as our vector
representation and now this is actually
equal to W 1 C 1 plus W 2 C 2 all right
and that looks very similar to various
equations we've had in recurrent neural
networks to where one was the history of
you know that we had in the past HT
minus 1 and another one is X 1 the next
word now it just turns out that C could
be both it could be single words or it
could be hidden dimensions and we'll go
through an example here in the next
couple of slides so the reason we call
this recursive and before recurrent is
that we use a also here the same W
parameters at all the nodes of the tree
so in order to compute any one of these
here we'll share the weight so we tie
the weights and basically have the same
W here to compute every single parent
vector yes
that is correct yeah the the word this
model is not it really depends on the
order of the words okay so this is the
main equation and again we see here this
is really essentially just a standard
single layer neural network just happens
to have as input two vectors that we
concatenate which the model doesn't
really know so the model is just a
single vector but the way we put them
together is by taking one vector from
the left child and one vector from the
right shop so the central equation of of
today
--------------------------------------------------- 14 (22) Parsing a sentence with an RNN
and so now how do we actually use
this to compute a tree structure that is
you know captures the grammar of that
sentence we basically and this is the
first simple version of how to describe
this and basically the only one we'll
describe in detail today so called
greedy search mechanism here we just
basically look at how how likely would
it be to combine the vector of the and
the vector of cat with this neural
network and you know that would get some
kind of vector representation first and
then a score that was just a linear
layer so again here the score which we
kind of skipped is just a simple inner
product same kind of score that we used
before so now we look at this and then
we'll just look at every possible pair
of words and how likely they would be to
combine to a reasonable syntactic phrase
and now it's just you know in dramatic
structure and according to linguists on
the is not a reasonable syntactic phrase
but the mat is a nice proper noun phrase
so that would get a large score and
likewise the cat is a very obvious very
simple combination of a determinant a
noun so we put those together
--------------------------------------------------- 15 (23) Parsing a sentence
so now the
cat here gets the higher score and in
this kind of greedy search mechanism we
will just say all right well then let's
combine those two let's instead of
having these two separate word vectors
here we will now just take the phrase
vector which is really just the output
of the hidden layer
so now the model basically has a one
vector here and that's the first vector
of the sequence and that vector
represents now the cat and now we have
basically have here the cat has a vector
and then still a set on the mat as each
one being a separate word vector and now
the model doesn't yet know how likely
would it be to combine the cats at and
so this is where the recursion comes in
the output of the first time we apply it
the neural network becomes the input to
that same neural network and that's why
it's recursive so now the cat set is
somewhat of a reasonable phrase you know
we could just say in the cat suits
instead of you know if the cat stands
and so this would get a reasonably large
score however the mat was an even more
obvious noun phrase
--------------------------------------------------- 16 (24) Parsing a sentence
and so we'll merge
those two nodes next and now again the
model doesn't know how likely it would
be to combine the word vector on with
the phrase vector the Matt and so we'll
again apply the same neural network yes
it's a great question we'll actually
them so boy it goes a little bit too far
so I can't go into too many details but
for those of you who actually have taken
the you know to 24 and no CQ I see you
okay it's just three names parsing and
chart parsing in chart parsing you can
actually make certain independence
assumptions kind of like you make markov
assumptions for language models we say I
don't care about anything else that came
before but right now this phrase is a
noun phrase and because of that you can
then say well I can find the global
optimum here because I can make certain
simplifying assumptions use dynamic
programming here you can't really use
that because the vectors on which you
make those assumptions are continuous
and so really changing the vector just a
little bit would change potentially the
overall score so while one phrase might
be locally the best highest-scoring
phrase it might not actually do to the
global optimum so all you could do here
is a so-called dynamic beam search but
don't worry if you don't weren't able to
follow that little sidenote so in the
end what we'll do is a CKY like beam
search but again don't worry about this
it's enough to understand so this greedy
procedure here for finding the best
Street
--------------------------------------------------- 17 (25) Parsing a sentence
okay so now we basically keep
building up this tree find the
highest-scoring potential candidate and
in the end have the full tree structure
yes
sorry can you speak a little louder
that's a so there are certain
constraints on these two that they have
to be symmetric that's actually an
interesting question there are none so
right now they can just be any arbitrary
matrix and it turns out that there are
interesting extensions that we'll go
into later in the lecture that actually
allow us to really understand a little
bit better how each what the role of
they are of these two blocks are their
left block and the right block well
we'll get to it in a couple slides but
yeah in general it's just a W matrix it
will be updated with SGD or other kinds
of optimization methods and there's no
no way to sort of force and force kind
of seventeen you don't want to enforce
symmetry because maybe on the left the
left phrase or left word might be more
important than the right one and any
other questions on how this sort of
greedy search procedure happened yet so
yes the same neural network here was
used for every single node computation
combined way back to work to balance
another
I just
so wonder for example you
alright so the question I guess is it's
a little fuzzy is it okay
to do this well it turns out it's okay
for tasks for certain tasks yeah it's
good enough to get you know these day of
the art performance on them yeah so the
question is is it good to have different
kinds of neural networks and actually
relax the assumptions so the way I
describe this so far is that these kinds
of models actually more recursive than
actual natural language natural language
tests sometimes a noun phrase inside a
relative clause inside a noun phrase
here we use the exact same neural
network at every single node of the tree
and so we'll actually relax that
assumption
later on the lecture
--------------------------------------------------- 18 (26) Max-Margin Framework - Details
so how do we
actually train this we will use a
similar max margin objective function to
what we had used before in one of the
earlier lectures but now we'll define
the score of the entire tree and we
don't just have a single window we have
a tree that actually was computed from
multiple different kinds of scores and
so the score of the full tree is for us
right now simply the sum of all the
scores at each node so let's define here
the score of a specific sentence X with
a specific tree Y we basically look at
all the nodes that that tree had and we
compute the scores at each of these
nodes and again these scores here were
just simple inner products with the same
view vector
--------------------------------------------------- 19 (27) Max-Margin Framework - Details
so here comes the the most
important and kind of interesting new
equation of of today's lecture basically
this is called max margin parsing and we
have here this max margin objective
function so let's walk through this
objective function very slowly what we
want to do we want to generally maximize
this function and we assume we have a
labeled training data set so we assume a
bunch of linguists sat down and said for
every sentence X I
I have I give you the correct tree why I
and now this again here was just the sum
of all the nodes of those trees and that
sum was just a sum of a bunch of inner
products right so again when you think
about you know how would you train this
model it's just a bunch of gradients of
you know a sum of inner products
underneath which you have a neural
network okay so that that's easy but now
if we just maximize all the scores of
all the correct trees well we could just
everything would go to infinity right we
just maximize everything well we
actually have to tell the model is how
to deal with finding the right tree by
itself and this is what the second part
here is so we're going to try to find
the maximum over this set and the set a
of X I is the set of all possible trees
that you could construct from X I and so
there if you're familiar with with
combinatorics they're Catalan many
potential binary trees so it's
exponentially many possible binary trees
you can actually compute that number and
blows up very very quickly
it's an exponentially many number of
trees so this is where we will have to
find some smarter way to go through them
and find the highest-scoring one and the
simplest one that I described was in
basically this greedy procedure here we
just take the highest-scoring current
set and hope that that will lead us
eventually to the highest-scoring tree
but of course that isn't necessarily
true here we found the correct tree but
maybe the model incorrectly would have
said cats at is the highest-scoring one
and then we couldn't recover that later
on right so this is basically a search
procedure and they're different ways to
do search and and in some ways if you
you know interested in kind of the
search aspect of machine learning and
they I then I think 221 is the right
kind of lecture takes sort of an
introduction to AI different kind of
search strategies all right so let's
assume for now that we find the
highest-scoring one simply with this
greedy procedure and we basically you
know do exactly what I described the
previous slides and now we define one
specific Y that is the maximum of all
the trees which we could build and now
because of this my
here we're going to try to minimize the
score of that highest-scoring tree and
let's assume let's ignore this part for
now if the highest-scoring tree that
we're now minimizing actually happens to
be the exact correct tree well then
we're done here right then why I and
this y are actually the same these two
cancel out and we're done
and now this is where the interesting
margin penalty comes in which as indeed
actually an important part of this
objective function and this margin here
essentially penalizes every incorrect
decision that you have made so if you
incorrectly combine two words then you
add one to that tree structure and what
that the result of that will be that
once you actually get the correct tree
here as Y and y actually is weii then
that Y will have a high score that is
higher up to a certain margin to the
next scoring but incorrect tree let's
parse that pretty complex sentence so
essentially what this Delta here does is
it encourages the model to make mistakes
it will add a bonus point to every
mistake the model makes and once it goes
past that bonus it actually makes the
right decision with a margin of Delta
which you usually just for every
incorrect decision we set it to one so
to score for the right decision will
that new one larger than the score of an
incorrect decision so in the beginning
here we encourage the model to basically
do the worst possible thing all right
and then model makes all these mistakes
and then you can tell them well these
were all wrong and you minimize all the
scores of these incorrect decisions and
that's that's where yeah that's sort of
the idea of the next margin loss
are there any questions about this yeah
so in almost every single weight in all
these different loss functions that I
always describe has a standard l2
penalty and all the weights the Delta
yeah the Delta does not it just
basically encourages the model to make
mistakes during the search procedure
it doesn't actually back up something in
itself great question yes
I
okay so again X I is the sentence so in
this case you know your cat sat on the
mat Y is the correct tree structure
basically linguists sat down went
through a lot of sentences in most cases
so-called penn treebank and in the
pantry bank they said all right for this
sentence this is the correct grammatical
analysis of that sentence
all right
yes can one turn be negative yes
so these scores here just inner products
right inner products of real numbers so
they can be very negative
--------------------------------------------------- 20 (28) Backpropagation Through Structure
all right so
how do we actually train this kind of
model and what does it what does this
look like again in some ways you could
just do this right away will require a
lot of thought I little embarrassing but
I actually had reinvented this whole
thing I didn't know it was it existed I
didn't have a name for what I was doing
so I actually had reinvented this whole
thing and only later I was like I'm
gonna call the recursive one recursive
known that or it's the best thing ever
and then I you know a couple days later
I'm like I should Google recursive
neural network and and of course some
people had invented it in the past but
have a more emotional connection now
since I had reinvented the wheel a
little bit so this is really just
standard like taking derivatives again
but there's you know they're cut a
couple of subtleties here so let's walk
through those quickly the main equations
that we had derived in their gory
details and you know you can read up in
a lecture notes now to again we have
these Delta's the error messages that
come from every layer and they're
basically being passed down the neural
network and we will update the different
W matrices here with this outer product
of the delta from the previous layer
times the activations of the current
layer so those equations will still be
the same but there are a couple of
couple of subtleties here namely the
following three differences that result
from having now the structured object
instead of just the same chain that goes
you know and has different weights at
every single layer of the network
--------------------------------------------------- 21 (29) BTS: 1) Sum derivatives of all nodes
so
let's walk through slowly through
through these differences so the first
one is we can actually just sum up all
the derivatives at all the nodes which
initially might not be that intuitive
right because in theory this is a
function of W which is a function of W
which is a function of W and so on goes
down the tree so just to give you an
intuition here
of how this comes about I basically just
wrote down all the gory details for a
very very simple sort of recurrent
function it's the same for recursion so
let's assume here it's just a tree that
happens to be a chain it just goes up
and up and up and there's only one input
X and you could even think through this
as just being single numbers W is just a
single number X is just a single number
and you know we just take the derivative
with respect to W now we can basically
write that out and assuming W here is
the same we'll you know apply the chain
rule but now you know when you take
derivative of a function in
multiplication you know have to take
derivative of both sides if their
parameters inside and this is really
basic algebra you basically end up with
this kind of equation and now if we
assumed that instead of having the same
W here you actually have a different one
this is W 2 and this is W 1 so assuming
that you had a different W at all the
different nodes in the tree and in this
case even simpler than just a simple
function you actually end up with
something that looks exactly the same if
you're in the end just get rid of the
indices again so this is fairly
straightforward you can just write down
the derivatives by yourselves and you'll
arrive at basically this kind of
property
--------------------------------------------------- 22 (30) BTS: 2) Split derivatives at each node
so really all we need to do is
we go up to tree once compute all our
hidden activations just like in forward
prop of any other neural network and
then we have to go down to tree once and
as we go down the main subtlety here is
now that because we concatenated the two
children vectors we have to somehow
split our error messages as we go down
so what do I mean by this
during forward propagation here the
parent is essentially computed using
those two child vectors that we had
concatenated and that means that when we
now compute out deltas our error
messages again with the similar the same
kinds of equations that we have here
then we will essentially just assume
that the Delta that comes from that
parent and is sent to the two children
it's just basic
a vector that we can now also split the
same way we concatenate it the children
we can split the error messages from one
side to the other
--------------------------------------------------- 23 (31) BTS: 3) Add error messages
all right and now the last part is that
we have scores at every node but every
node is also part of the score
computation of another node namely the
parent nodes right so we have here c1
and c2 they have a score and we want to
minimize or maximize that score
depending on whether that phrase is in
the right or a wrong parse tree but now
their parent will be the left child in
this case in this kind of visualization
here the left child of yet another
combination and so when we take the
derivatives with respect to W here of
the parent that will basically send
messages all the way down to the leaf
nodes every node of the tree sends error
messages down all to all its children in
the tree and so just as before if we
have two different objective functions
on top of the same layer we basically
just add the error messages coming from
both so we have here 1 Delta message
that comes from the score that we
compute and another Delta message that
comes from the parent that uses this for
computing another score
--------------------------------------------------- 24 (32) BTS Python Code: forwardProp
and you'll
actually have to implement this in your
last problem set either this or
convolutional neural network which we'll
go over next week even more complicated
so it's very important to understand
this and I'll give you a little bit of a
hint here for the last problem set
largely because I want you to be able to
solve the problem set 3 quickly so you
can have a really cool epic class
project which is very important and I
think of the most interesting last thing
so the output for most of you from this
class so here we basically walked slowly
through some Python code for the forward
propagation and just to show you how
similar this is to all the other neural
networks that you already have with
these three subtle differences so you
have some kind of recursion that you can
implement there are different ways you
can implement recursion in tree
structures but basically to compute the
hidden activation for a specific No
we just basically sack here these to the
left child and the right child and their
hidden activations which in the
beginning again could just be war
vectors and then we just basically have
a dot product or you know multiplied
this w matrix times this concatenated
child vector so that's fairly
straightforward and then we add the bias
term here and then we apply our element
wise non-linearity which in this case
could be the rail you could be ten h2
and so on alright so that's basically
the equation of the recursive neural
network that I put into a red box and
then we just compute for instance a
score or in this case here a softmax
probability again or compute the softmax
to get a probability for some kind of
class so we could assume WS for instance
are here our soft mix weights and you've
already implemented this as well and one
interesting side note here sometimes you
will actually run into stability issues
when you implement these kinds of models
especially for rectified linear units
your numbers can get very large and so
this is an interesting sort of trick or
hack to prevent overflow and your
floating-point operations which is you
just subtract the maximum from those
numbers and you should verify that this
doesn't really change the probabilities
and then we take the exponent of this
sum over the exponents and that is
basically the probability here for any
kind of class for any kind of node so
what does that mean we can now basically
classify that you know the keyboard is a
neutral phrase for instance and
sentiment and then the buggy keyboard is
you know a negative phrase and buggy
keyboard which I really really hate it
when I have to type on it is now a riri
negative phrase right and so you can
basically classify all the phrases as
you combine different words differently
and this will eventually lead to being
able to really classify that I this
movie didn't care about cleverness wit
or any other kind of intelligent humor
while having a bunch of phrases that are
really positive at the end at the inn
somewhere in the beginning it says it
doesn't care about it and then it
becomes negative so this is basically
what this kind of model can do
--------------------------------------------------- 25 (33) BTS Python Code: backProp
all right now comes the interesting part
which is the backdrop so I mentioned
there are three three different things
here so let's walk let's walk through
this here we have the deltas which just
comes from the softmax so you've already
all derived that in all the gory details
and you've implemented it so this one
should be fairly straightforward of how
you compute here your deltas and again
here you have an interesting you know W
transpose times Delta that's the first
one now here comes the interesting
settled notion of having a delta
potentially from the parent node as well
as from your own prediction and if you
have a parent which basically every
internal tree does then you will just
add your two Delta's the Delta that you
have from your own softmax or your own
inner product for your scoring function
plus the error that comes from your
parents so this is also recursive kind
of function and then we take our element
wise non-linearity here f prime of Z and
then then it's fairly straightforward if
you are a leave vector and this is
actually an interesting notion here too
you can train your word vectors as part
of the entire recursive neural network
model so in some cases if your data set
is so large for what you actually care
about you don't even have to run work to
Veck or Glove or any other kind of word
vector separately you can just train a
word vectors as part of the model again
everything is a parameter the word
vectors are parameter you just add them
and then as you go through the tree and
you send down different error messages
and whatever kind of tree you know you
have Delta message coming from here send
down to both of the both of the children
keep sending it down at the end they
arrive at the word vectors so why not
tell the word vectors well if you just
changed around a little bit in your
vector space you might actually do a
better job in that classification
somewhere higher up in the tree and that
pushes the word vectors to be somewhere
else so basically you can collect here
all your derivatives for your word
vectors to just taking the Delta
that has arrived now at the word vectors
and if you're not a leaf node if you're
not at the very bottom of the tree but
you're somewhere an internal node then
comes in the standard stuff here we have
the derivative of W will just be Delta
outer product with the current
activation the current activation in
this case was the left child and the
right child so we just concatenate those
again and get exactly here the main
equation we had derived before just an
outer product of the delta from the
previous layer the outer product with
the activation at that current layer and
same with WP here we had there so just
you add the deltas to the derivative of
B and now you compute the next Delta to
go down one layer with this equation we
had derived which is just W transposed
times your current Delta and now you
send those to the two children and
eventually the F prime here again will
happen at that node all right so this
hopefully will help you a lot in in
problem set three but you'll actually
have to derive it and you know I didn't
add all the details and you have to
really understand how to send around
Delta's in a different kind of tree
structure so still still a lot of work
so don't don't wait for too long and
thinking this is the entire thing yes oh
this one here is an Audemars product or
an element-wise multiplication
--------------------------------------------------- 26 (34) BTS: Optimization
all right so now we have all our
derivatives and we basically do the
standard stuff which is we take some
off-the-shelf optimizer such as SGD
which we had used can also use l-bfgs in
most most cases you know standard
optimizers and matlab or Python actually
have both of these as options we had
also mentioned before to actually use a
degrade and this is also very useful
here for for our model so we can
actually update here again our theta at
the next time step of the optimization
by dividing over the gradients of all
the previous time steps we mentioned
this in one of the tips and tricks in a
previous lecture and it turns out this
is also a subtle difference here that
you don't we don't really have to go
into too many details with but because
you have here non continuous objective
function imagine you change the
highest-scoring tree and now all the
sudden because of one little subtle
difference in the score at a lower layer
and this greedy search procedure now
it's a completely different tree now
this is a you know non continuity but it
turns out you just still take your
derivatives and I use sup gradient so
what this means in practice is will
basically compute the score here of the
correct tree maximize all those take
derivatives with respect to all the
parameters and increase all those scores
find here the highest-scoring negative
tree with our search procedure the
highest-scoring
incorrect tree sorry and then we just
minimize all those scores so they're
just two trees at every time step one
tree is the correct one we maximize it
scores one tree is the highest-scoring
incorrect one minimize dos once they're
both exactly the same well then those
two terms cancel each other out and
you're done with that tree and you can
ignore it and only now try to optimize
over trees you haven't yet correctly
parsed
--------------------------------------------------- 27 (35) Discussion: Simple RNN
alright so that was the most basic
definition of a single matrix recursive
neural network and those actually obtain
reasonably good results and I had a
bunch of papers or state-of-the-art
results and
different tasks I'll actually cover some
of those in the next lecture but one
interesting problem of them and this is
similar to the recurrent neural networks
where we had the same W at every single
node to is that they can't really
capture all the complex phenomena of how
you should compute and map now all these
different phrases into the same vector
space it's a pretty complex procedure
we're asking here a single W which
essentially boils down to just you know
some affine transformation that you you
know add to two child vectors we asked
it to really capture all the
complexities of how to create meaning in
a language right it's it's a little too
much to ask of a single matrix W were
essentially asking it to combine
different syntactic categories I have an
adjective here and a noun here and I
multiply it the first part of my W
matrix times the adjective vector and
then the right part times the noun
vector but now you know the next layer I
might have a verb phrase plus now that
combined noun phrase and now I take that
same W matrix and multiply it with a
verb and I expect that transformation to
also map it into a reasonable part of
the vector space it's a lot to ask of a
single model or single W matrix
--------------------------------------------------- 28 (36) Solution: Syntactically-Untied RNN
and so
the idea here is that because we're
already in grammar land and we already
have these syntactic tree structures why
not use them a little more and
essentially condition these composition
functions these neural network layers
that have only a single W and instead
untie the weights relax the assumption
this comes back to a question that was
asked before which is should we really
use the same W here at every single node
of the tree and what we could do instead
is actually condition these composition
functions on what kinds of syntactic
categories they're actually combining
and this is this an interesting notion
here so let's walk through an example so
here this is the standard recursive
neural network where we use the same W
here at every single node in a tree and
now let's assume we have actually some
knowledge about what these word vectors
are
and this knowledge comes in the form of
discrete categories so let's say a B and
C here capital letters are actual
discrete categories so maybe this is you
know I so it's a personal pronoun and we
know this vector here is a personal
pronoun like is a verb and cats is a
noun and so see here is this is a noun
phrase B here is this is a verb and now
we'll actually use a W matrix here that
we select different W matrices we have a
large set of them usually around 80 or
so and in depending on what syntactic
categories you have to use different W
so here we have the first W that
combines syntactic categories where the
left child is of the syntactic category
B and the right child is of syntactic
category C
--------------------------------------------------- 29 (37) Solution: Compositional Vector Grammars
yes right so how do you get
the syntactic categories basically you
use a very simple model that is not very
accurate but basically just looks at the
summary statistics of your corpus your
training corpus you know what the right
trees are all right the linguists again
had sat down created for instance penn
treebank an infantry bank you can know
all right these kinds of things only
ever combine this kind of way and just
taking those counts basically boils down
to probabilistic context-free grammar
and we can't really go into the details
in this in this class but it's a very
simple generative model of of parse
trees and in its most simple form is
very fast but it's not very accurate but
it turns out it's good enough to give us
a bunch of candidates which we can then
go over and it's also good enough to
help us condition and get syntactic
categories
yes
you we will actually compute this final
score as the sum of the recursive no net
or score as well as log likelihood from
the pcfg but you we're not going to
weight them but we will get some
weighting coming from now having
different composition matrices W and
I'll show you in a second what these
look like yes it's a good question
I think you actually have the option
here to also use a deeper network you
could also just classify each of these
vectors here and it's separate there's a
separate neural net we're going to say
alright I classify this as a verb phrase
if I said this is a noun phrase and then
I'd condition my my composition function
based on these classification problems
it's actually also a reasonable option
--------------------------------------------------- 29 (37) Solution: Compositional Vector Grammars
all right so basically for yes
it's a great question so we will
actually in the simplest case just
assume let's say we have a model that
gives us for each sentence 200
candidates where we know the syntactic
categories of every single phrase and
word and this in our case will be a very
simple fast pcfg model don't worry if
you don't really understand PCF jeez if
you've taken 224 good for you if not
let's just assume you have some Oracle
that gives you for each sentence 200 or
so candidates of what could the right
structure be and ideally you know in
over 95% of the cases
one of those 200 is actually the right
one it just turns out the model that
gives them to you doesn't actually know
which one is the right one and so it
helps us basically to prune very
unlikely candidates which is just a
speed hack we could use a neural network
but then you have lots of matrix
multiplications in sight to compute all
these potential candidates and this one
helps you and it also provides you some
core syntactic categories of the
children
--------------------------------------------------- 29 (37) Solution: Compositional Vector Grammars
and so we will call this full
model here compositional vector grammar
basically combines a simple model like a
pcfg with a more complex recursive
neural network
--------------------------------------------------- 31 (39) Related work for recursive neural networks
there's been a bunch of
work on these and in most cases it's
quite different they assume fix tree
structures they didn't actually do next
margin learning they didn't actually use
a large large trees and long sentences
--------------------------------------------------- 32 (40) Related Work for parsing
and so on there's also been a lot of
work in parsing where people have
basically taken the manual feature
engineering approach and try to improve
the original simple pcfg where you just
say this is a noun phrase and without
going into too many details here you can
basically look at all the errors you're
making and try to describe each of the
categories with some richer but still
discrete representation so in some ways
and sort of historically this kind of
model extends all these other ideas from
taking counts over discrete kinds of
information to just representing
everything as a non discrete as a
continuous vector representation
--------------------------------------------------- 33 (41) Experiments
so the
numbers here are in
some ways not that interesting there's
lots of work on this task a lot of
researchers and natural language
processing care about parsing and so
there's been lots of different different
work here what's interesting here is if
we have the same weight matrix W at
every node of the tree we actually don't
get a very competitive parser but once
we allowed the syntactic untying having
different W matrices we actually get a
very very good parser there's still
other ones that take into consideration
even more external data but they're much
much slower at both training and testing
than in this one and the way we measure
this years again with f1 where we have
precision and recall over the various
nodes in the
--------------------------------------------------- 34 (42) SU-RNN Analysis
tree what's more
interesting is that linguists had a
certain notion of soft edward's in fact
one of the baseline models here from
Collins tries to lexical eyes these
parsing decisions and say well this is a
noun phrase with a cat inside for
instance or in this verb phrase here may
be the verb matters more than a noun
because in the end the action sort of
matters more than maybe the things that
depend on the action what's cool is this
model actually learned what linguists
had themselves sort of come up with by
trying to analyze grammatical structure
in language so it for instance learned
that when I combine a determiner like
the or a with a noun phrase like cat or
Church or Windows that the noun phrase
actually matters more so what do we see
here this is essentially exactly this
kind of matrix the left block of is the
matrix that is multiplied with the left
vector the right block is the block that
is multiplied with the right child of
that phrase and now here we basically
just visualize how large our elements
are and I had brought up in a previous
lecture that there's sort of this hack
of initializing these matrices with
identity matrices and that's exactly
what we did here too we basically have
we start by
having to block identity matrices so the
default in the very beginning of the
model if you don't know anything is
actually just average to - yeah you
start here with 1/2 times these 2
identity matrices so you have here 1/2
times and any matrix basically just
comes down to 1/2 C plus C 1 plus 1/2 of
C 2 so and then you know of course you
apply to non-linearity but in general
when you start out with that's what you
get and then slowly but surely the model
pushes itself to basically start to
ignore more and more with its deck hat
or a cat or this cat or that cat
literally and just realize ok the most
important thing here for the semantics
of the resulting phrase is that it's a
cat not that it is that or this array
and that's that's really neat right the
model here learned something that
linguists had also come up with through
many years of research but a model
learned it just from looking at lots of
data
--------------------------------------------------- 35 (43) Analysis of resulting vector representations
what's more interesting is we can
actually now look at what these word
vectors and phrase vectors are capturing
so we can look at nearest neighbors in
the phrase vector space and just like
report vectors the word vector space is
basically captured syntactic and
semantic information nouns were closer
to other nouns and then once you zoom in
the semantically similar nouns are
closer to other semantically similar
nouns the same thing it's kind of true
for phrases it's of course much harder
because in general for most sentences
and most reasonably sized score Prada it
might not be that many other sentences
that are very very similar to that
sentence this is a much more complex
space and a lot of NOP researchers had
actually initially argued that it's
almost ridiculous to squeeze a variable
length sentence structure into a fixed
vector representation I think now it's
becoming more and more common and with
the results from machine translation
that we covered in the last last week's
lecture we actually see that well it is
a reasonable enough representation to
really capture a lot of subtle
information so here what we did is we
he cooked the top vector of one of these
sentences and we mapped a bunch of
different sentences in this case from
the penn treebank
into this vector space and then we pick
one sentence and then we look at the
nearest neighbors of that sentence in
the resulting vector space and for the
sentence all the figures are adjusted
for seasonal variations the closest
sentence to that one is all the numbers
are adjusted for seasonal fluctuations
so here it basically just learned well
if I have two similar word vectors
variations and fluctuations and figures
and numbers but the rest of the tree
structure is the same well that you know
still keeps them the same so that's
maybe not that impressive
right but the next one is interesting
all the figures are adjusted to remove
usual seasonal patterns so here it
actually learned that to remove usual
seasonal patterns it's kind of similar
to seasonal fluctuations or adjusting
for those and so it actually had some
sort of invariance to adjusting here a
hole verb phrase versus adjusting just
directly this noun phrase and
knight-ridder a bunch of organizations
wouldn't comment on the offer the model
learned that that's somewhat similar to
how score declining to say what country
plates the order or coastal wouldn't
disclose the terms so it learned here
that you know two wouldn't comment and
decline to say and wouldn't disclose are
similar kinds of things that companies
would do and personally I was very
excited when when I saw these kinds of
results in 2000 2010 and I was one of
the reasons I sort of went into you know
deeper and deeper into deep learning
because it's kind of learned some
interesting patterns that we didn't
explicitly tell the model to try to
capture and basically was also the first
step into thinking about applying these
models to paraphrase detection or
understanding semantic similarity
between different sentences and for
those of you or think about you know
summarization this is also an important
kind of result for sort of sentence
summarization not including the same
sentence as multiple times
--------------------------------------------------- 36 (44) SU-RNN Analysis
another interesting one was exactly this
example that I brought up from from the
beginning with the entity the PP
attachment ambiguity so the
prepositional phrases and where they
should attach should they attach to
nouns or the verbs so here the question
is can we transfer semantic information
from a single related example so here
the idea is we add two training
sentences and then we test on these two
test sentences and these all these four
sentences are actually incorrectly
parsed when you take any or most of the
standard parsers because they were
usually trained on a penn treebank which
comes from the Wall Street Journal and
The Wall Street Journal just doesn't
talk much about eating spaghetti so
they're almost all incorrect or all for
most parses and then we basically add
these and now because we use word
vectors to make these decisions we don't
need to see exactly spoon and meat at
training time because at sorry a test
time because a training time we saw fork
and from our word vectors we know that
fork and spoon are actually two similar
kinds of things they have similar vector
representations so the hope here is
because we don't think of these as
discrete entities and we just keep
counts in a probabilistic model and we
keep counts for fork and now well you
know if you'd never seen spoon before
your counts for for fork don't really
help you if however you learn the neural
network model that takes into input
takes as input something that looks like
a vector in this area of the space and
you find something else that is in that
similar space such as you know fork and
spoon having closed word vectors
--------------------------------------------------- 37 (45) SU-RNN Analysis
then
there's some chance that this will
happen and that's exactly what did
happen which is we had here the original
Stanford factor parser which didn't get
the PP e attachments correct and the
compositional vector grammar I described
before correctly put the prepositional
phrase here with a spoon to the verb
phrase and with meat to the spaghetti
yes sorry sagen how are the children is
my uh-huh
mm-hmm oh this one right here so the
question is how did we actually get from
the binary tree structures that I
described to ternary ones it turns out
any grammar and Chomsky normal form can
actually binarized and then you can have
a deterministic procedure to get back to
basically map between a binary version
and one that isn't binarized and still
recover the exact same grammar and so
this is basically a deterministic sort
of post-processing step to then create
create ternary structures you could also
in the greedy search procedure actually
have a double u that just has three
blocks W 1 W 2 and W 3 and you just
multiply it with three word vectors and
compute you know again a parent vector P
for that but it just turns out that if
you try to use CQI like chart parsing
then that blows up your complexity even
more so you rather just do it as a
post-processing step don't worry if you
didn't understand all that things I just
--------------------------------------------------- 38 (46) Labeling in Recursive Neural Networks
okay so I showed you in the code that we
can use these parent vectors also to
compute any kind of class right we can
predict sentiment for every phrase we
can predict the syntactic categories
lots of different things we can predict
and we will do that with the softmax
classifier at every node and again we
train it similarly to before and in the
case of the actual parser we can
actually train this by having two scores
and we just add the two errors the max
margin error we add the Cross enter pair
and we just take derivatives with
respect to both same way we did before
--------------------------------------------------- 39 (47) Scene Parsing
so now let's think about scene parsing
it's actually in some ways and this is
kind of a fun side note for the last
three minutes that shows you that once
you are really good at deep learning for
natural language processing you really
now have a tool in your bag that lets
you do almost anything that is related
to data because almost every data can be
represented as some kind of vector and
you can use these kinds of technique
for lots of other things so last little
three-minute side note here on computer
vision where you could kind of assume
that even in scene images you have a
similar principle of compositionality
going on where you can define the
meaning of the scene as also a function
of the smaller regions you know there's
a bush there's some people there's a you
know a roof they're a bunch of different
objects here or parts of a larger
structure you have a tree now the single
parts of the structure composed to form
a building and you know then all these
various objects interact in certain ways
--------------------------------------------------- 40 (48) Algorithm for Parsing Images
and it turns out that I don't need to
actually describe to you in many details
how you would learn how to combine
little regions because it's the exact
same neural network that we just
described for sentence parsing we
basically the main difference here is
instead of starting reward vectors for
words we actually start with feature
vectors for little regions and images
there's some computer vision technology
and how to actually compute those and
program that but let's assume we have a
vector a presentation that captures
features of small image regions well now
we use that exact same neural network we
can have you know a bunch of neighbors
now it's not just the left word and the
right word but all the regions that are
neighboring a certain other region and
image we can compute scores for whether
we should combine them or not we have
some training data for that that says
you know this part all these different
regions are actually part of the same
you know building or our street or group
of people or three or whatever and then
we lower we increase scores for things
we want to combine we decrease scores
for things we don't want to combine and
that way we can build these whole
structures
--------------------------------------------------- 41 (49) Multi-class segmentation
and this kind of model
actually you know back in 2011 was a
state of the art model since then
actually people have have come up with
even better models all of which I think
are also deep learning based but here
you can basically see you know what
kinds of things that labels as Street or
trees or buildings and so on and so so
yeah hopefully that shows you that
really the
kinds of tools you learn here and we've
already seen this for some class
projects some of you are using these
tools to understand genetic language
instead of natural language but really
it's a very general set of tools that
that you're learning here alright and
that's it for today